<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="screencopy_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2021 Andri Yngvason

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="screen content capturing on client buffers">
    This protocol allows clients to ask the compositor to copy part of the
    screen content to a client buffer.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
    backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
    may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
    Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
    the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
    Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
    version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
    interface version number is reset.
  </description>

  <interface name="zext_screencopy_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager to inform clients and begin capturing">
      This object is a manager which offers requests to start capturing from a
      source.
    </description>

    <request name="capture_output">
      <description summary="capture an output">
        Create a capturing surface for an output
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="new_id" interface="zext_screencopy_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zext_screencopy_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a frame ready for copy">
      This object represents a surface that's being captured.

      After a screencopy surface is created, buffer_info events will be emitted
      from the compositor to tell the client which buffer types and formats are
      supported for reading from the surface.

      When the client knows all the buffer attributes, it can create a buffer,
      attach it to the screencopy surface using the "attach_buffer" request,
      set the buffer damage using the "damage_buffer" request and then call
      the "commit" request.

      After "commit" has been called, the next time that a buffer is committed
      by the compositor, the contents of that buffer will be copied to the one
      committed to the screencopy surface. A series of events will be generated,
      ending with the "ready" event, which means that the buffer is ready to be
      used and a buffer may be committed to the surface again.

      The "failed" event may be sent at any time. When this happens, the client
      must destroy the surface. Depending on the failure reason, the client can
      create a new surface to replace it.
    </description>

    <enum name="failure_reason">
      <entry name="unspec" value="0"/>
      <entry name="invalid_buffer" value="1"/>
      <entry name="output_missing" value="2"/>
      <entry name="output_disabled" value="3"/>
      <entry name="unknown_seat" value="4"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="options" bitfield="true">
      <entry name="none" value="0"/>
      <entry name="immediate" value="1"/>
      <entry name="render_cursors" value="2"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="buffer_type">
      <entry name="wl_shm" value="0"/>
      <entry name="dmabuf" value="1"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="buffer_info">
      <description summary="buffer information">
        Provides information about buffer parameters that need to be used for
        the main image. This event is sent for every supported buffer type
        after the surface is created.

        The stride parameter is invalid for dmabuf and may be set to 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="buffer_type" summary="buffer type"/>
      <arg name="format" type="uint" summary="buffer drm format"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="buffer width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="buffer height"/>
      <arg name="stride" type="uint" summary="buffer stride"/>
    </event>

    <event name="cursor_buffer_info">
      <description summary="cursor buffer information">
        Provides information about buffer parameters that need to be used for
        the cursor image. This event is sent for every supported buffer type
        after the surface is created, and it may be different for each seat.

        The default seat will be referred to as "default" within this protocol,
        whether it be named so by the compositor or not.

        The stride parameter is invalid for dmabuf and may be set to 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat_name" type="string" summary="seat name"/>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="buffer_type" summary="buffer type"/>
      <arg name="format" type="uint" summary="buffer drm format"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="buffer width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="buffer height"/>
      <arg name="stride" type="uint" summary="buffer stride"/>
    </event>

    <event name="init_done">
      <description summary="surface initialisation done">
        This event is sent once when all buffer info events have been sent.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="attach_buffer">
      <description summary="attach buffer to surface">
        Attach a buffer to the surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="buffer" type="object" interface="wl_buffer"/>
    </request>

    <request name="damage_buffer">
      <description summary="damage buffer">
        Apply damage to the buffer which is to be committed next.

        This is for optimisation purposes. The compositor may use this
        information to reduce copying.

        The client must submit damage if it's using multiple buffers. Otherwise,
        the server might not copy into damaged regions of the buffer.

        These coordinates originate in the upper left corner of the buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="uint" summary="region x coordinates"/>
      <arg name="y" type="uint" summary="region y coordinates"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="region width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="region height"/>
    </request>

    <request name="attach_cursor_buffer">
      <description summary="attach cursor buffer to surface">
        Attach a named cursor buffer to the surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="buffer" type="object" interface="wl_buffer"/>
      <arg name="seat_name" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="damage_cursor_buffer">
      <description summary="damage cursor buffer">
        Apply damage to a named cursor buffer which is to be committed next.

        The whole cursor buffer will be considered damaged.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat_name" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit surface">
        Commit the screencopy surface.

        The frame will be copied to the surface on next output commit. A ready
        event is generated when the buffer is ready.

        If the "immediate" flag is set, the compositor must present a frame to
        the client as soon as possible.

        If the "render_cursors" flag is set, cursors shall be composited onto the
        main surface. Otherwise, the compositor should try to leave them out, if
        possible.
      </description>
      <arg name="options" type="uint" enum="options"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete this object">
        Destroys the surface. This request can be sent at any time by the
        client.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="transform">
      <description summary="carries the output transform">
        This event is sent before the ready event and holds the output transform
        of the source buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="transform" type="int" enum="wl_output.transform"/>
    </event>

    <event name="damage">
      <description summary="carries the coordinates of the damaged region">
        This event is sent before the ready event. It may be generated multiple
        times for each commit.

        The arguments describe a box around an area that has changed since the
        last ready event.

        These coordinates originate in the upper left corner of the buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="uint" summary="damaged x coordinates"/>
      <arg name="y" type="uint" summary="damaged y coordinates"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="current width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="current height"/>
    </event>

    <event name="cursor_info">
      <description summary="cursor specific information">
        This event is generated for each cursor buffer that was attached to the
        surface and for which the cursor is currently focused on the surface.
        It is generated once for each cursor buffer before the ready event.

        Cursors outside the surface do not get captured and no event will be
        generated for them.

        If the cursor image has changed, the cursor buffer will have been
        updated and the "has_damage" argument will be set to 1; otherwise 0.

        The hotspot position is relative to the cursor buffer.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat_name" type="string" summary="seat name"/>
      <arg name="has_damage" type="int" summary="buffer has changes"/>
      <arg name="position_x" type="int" summary="position x coordinates"/>
      <arg name="position_y" type="int" summary="position y coordinates"/>
      <arg name="hotspot_x" type="int" summary="hotspot x coordinates"/>
      <arg name="hotspot_y" type="int" summary="hotspot y coordinates"/>
    </event>

    <event name="failed">
      <description summary="commit failed">
        This event indicates that the attempted frame copy has failed.

        After receiving this event, the client should destroy the object.
      </description>
      <arg name="reason" type="uint" enum="failure_reason"/>
    </event>

    <event name="commit_time">
      <description summary="indicates the commit time of the frame">
        This event indicates the time at which the frame is committed to be
        scanned out.

        The timestamp is expressed as tv_sec_hi, tv_sec_lo, tv_nsec triples,
        each component being an unsigned 32-bit value. Whole seconds are in
        tv_sec which is a 64-bit value combined from tv_sec_hi and tv_sec_lo,
        and the additional fractional part in tv_nsec as nanoseconds. Hence,
        for valid timestamps tv_nsec must be in [0, 999999999]. The seconds part
        may have an arbitrary offset at start.
      </description>
      <arg name="tv_sec_hi" type="uint"
           summary="high 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_sec_lo" type="uint"
           summary="low 32 bits of the seconds part of the timestamp"/>
      <arg name="tv_nsec" type="uint"
           summary="nanoseconds part of the timestamp"/>
    </event>

    <event name="ready">
      <description summary="indicates frame is available for reading">
        Called as soon as the frame is copied, indicating it is available
        for reading.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
