<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<protocol name="text_input_unstable_v3">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2012, 2013 Intel Corporation
    Copyright © 2015, 2016 Jan Arne Petersen
    Copyright © 2017, 2018 Red Hat, Inc.
    Copyright © 2018 Purism SPC

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zwp_text_input_v3" version="1">
    <description summary="text input">
      The zwp_text_input_v3 interface represents text input and input methods
      associated with a seat. It provides enter/leave events to follow the
      text input focus for a seat.

      Requests are used to enable/disable the text-input object and set
      state information like surrounding and selected text or the content type.
      The information about the entered text is sent to the text-input object
      via the pre-edit and commit_string events.

      Text is valid UTF-8 encoded, indices and lengths are in bytes. Indices
      have to always point to the first byte of an UTF-8 encoded code point.
      Lengths are not allowed to contain just a part of an UTF-8 encoded code
      point.

      Focus moving throughout surfaces will result in the emission of
      zwp_text_input_v3.enter and zwp_text_input_v3.leave events. The focused
      surface must perform zwp_text_input_v3.enable and
      zwp_text_input_v3.disable requests as the keyboard focus moves across
      editable and non-editable elements of the UI. Those two requests are not
      expected to be paired with each other, the compositor must be able to
      handle consecutive series of the same request.

      State is sent by the state requests (set_surrounding_text,
      set_content_type and set_cursor_rectangle) and a commit request.
      After an enter event or disable request all state information is
      invalidated and needs to be resent by the client.

      This protocol defines requests and events necessary for regular clients
      to communicate with an input method. The zwp_input_method protocol
      defines the interfaces necessary to implement standalone input methods.
      If a compositor implements both interfaces, it will be the arbiter of the
      communication between both.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
      backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
      may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
      Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
      the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
      Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
      version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
      interface version number is reset.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the wp_text_input">
       Destroy the wp_text_input object. Also disables all surfaces enabled
       through this wp_text_input object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="enable_flags" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="enable flags">
       Enable flags is a bitmask to allow to modify the behavior of the text
       input.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0x0" summary="no special behavior"/>
      <entry name="can_show_preedit" value="0x1" summary="hints that the UI is capable of showing pre-edit text"/>
      <entry name="toggle_input_panel" value="0x2" summary="requests toggling input panel (eg. on-screen keyboard)"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="enable">
      <description summary="Request text input to be enabled">
        Requests text input on a surface.
      </description>
      <arg name="flags" type="uint" enum="enable_flags" summary="details of the enable request"/>
    </request>

    <request name="disable">
      <description summary="Disable text input on a surface">
        Explicitly disable text input in a surface (typically when there is no
        focus on any text entry inside the surface).
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_surrounding_text">
      <description summary="sets the surrounding text">
       Sets the surrounding plain text around the input position. Text is
       UTF-8 encoded. Cursor is the byte offset within the surrounding text.
       Anchor is the byte offset of the selection anchor within the
       surrounding text. If there is no selected text, anchor is the same as
       cursor.

       Make sure to always send some text before and after the cursor
       except when the cursor is at the beginning or end of text.

       There is a maximum length of wayland messages so text can not be
       longer than 4000 bytes.

       Values set with this request are double-buffered. They will get applied
       on the next zwp_text_input_v3.commit request.

       The initial value for text is an empty string, and the initial values for
       cursor and anchor are 0.
      </description>
      <arg name="text" type="string"/>
      <arg name="cursor" type="int"/>
      <arg name="anchor" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="content_hint" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="content hint">
       Content hint is a bitmask to allow to modify the behavior of the text
       input.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0x0" summary="no special behavior"/>
      <entry name="completion" value="0x1" summary="suggest word completions"/>
      <entry name="spellcheck" value="0x2" summary="suggest word corrections"/>
      <entry name="auto_capitalization" value="0x4" summary="switch to uppercase letters at the start of a sentence"/>
      <entry name="lowercase" value="0x8" summary="prefer lowercase letters"/>
      <entry name="uppercase" value="0x10" summary="prefer uppercase letters"/>
      <entry name="titlecase" value="0x20" summary="prefer casing for titles and headings (can be language dependent)"/>
      <entry name="hidden_text" value="0x40" summary="characters should be hidden"/>
      <entry name="sensitive_data" value="0x80" summary="typed text should not be stored"/>
      <entry name="latin" value="0x100" summary="just Latin characters should be entered"/>
      <entry name="multiline" value="0x200" summary="the text input is multiline"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="content_purpose">
      <description summary="content purpose">
       The content purpose allows to specify the primary purpose of a text
       input.

       This allows an input method to show special purpose input panels with
       extra characters or to disallow some characters.
      </description>
      <entry name="normal" value="0" summary="default input, allowing all characters"/>
      <entry name="alpha" value="1" summary="allow only alphabetic characters"/>
      <entry name="digits" value="2" summary="allow only digits"/>
      <entry name="number" value="3" summary="input a number (including decimal separator and sign)"/>
      <entry name="phone" value="4" summary="input a phone number"/>
      <entry name="url" value="5" summary="input an URL"/>
      <entry name="email" value="6" summary="input an email address"/>
      <entry name="name" value="7" summary="input a name of a person"/>
      <entry name="password" value="8" summary="input a password (combine with sensitive_data hint)"/>
      <entry name="pin" value="9" summary="input is a numeric password (combine with sensitive_data hint)"/>
      <entry name="date" value="10" summary="input a date"/>
      <entry name="time" value="11" summary="input a time"/>
      <entry name="datetime" value="12" summary="input a date and time"/>
      <entry name="terminal" value="13" summary="input for a terminal"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_content_type">
      <description summary="set content purpose and hint">
       Sets the content purpose and content hint. While the purpose is the
       basic purpose of an input field, the hint flags allow to modify some
       of the behavior.

       Values set with this request are double-buffered. They will get applied
       on the next zwp_text_input_v3.commit request.

       The initial value for hint is none, and the initial value for purpose
       is normal.
      </description>
      <arg name="hint" type="uint" enum="content_hint"/>
      <arg name="purpose" type="uint" enum="content_purpose"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_cursor_rectangle">
      <description summary="set cursor position">
       Sets the cursor outline as a x, y, width, height rectangle in surface
       local coordinates.

       Allows the compositor to put a window with word suggestions near the
       cursor.

       Values set with this request are double-buffered. They will get applied
       on the next zwp_text_input_v3.commit request.

       The initial values describing a cursor rectangle are invalid. That means
       the pending cursor rectangle values must be set before the first commit
       request.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit state">
       Text input state (content purpose, content hint, surrounding text,
       cursor rectangle) is conceptually double-buffered. Protocol requests
       modify the pending state, as opposed to the current state in use by the
       input method. A commit request atomically applies all pending state,
       replacing the current state. After commit, the new pending state is as
       documented for each related request.

       The current and pending state never changes unless noted otherwise.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="enter">
      <description summary="enter event">
       Notification that this seat's text-input focus is on a certain surface.

       When the seat has the keyboard capability the text-input focus follows
       the keyboard focus.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </event>

    <event name="leave">
      <description summary="leave event">
       Notification that this seat's text-input focus is no longer on
       a certain surface. The client should reset any preedit string previously
       set.

       The leave notification is sent before the enter notification
       for the new focus.

       When the seat has the keyboard capability the text-input focus follows
       the keyboard focus.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </event>

    <event name="preedit_string">
      <description summary="pre-edit">
       Notify when a new composing text (pre-edit) should be set around the
       current cursor position. Any previously set composing text should
       be removed.
      </description>
      <arg name="text" type="string" allow-null="true"/>
      <arg name="cursor" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <event name="commit_string">
      <description summary="text commit">
       Notify when text should be inserted into the editor widget. The text to
       commit could be either just a single character after a key press or the
       result of some composing (pre-edit).

       The text argument could be also null if some text is removed (see
       zwp_text_input_v3.delete_surrounding_text).

       Any previously set composing text should be removed.
      </description>
      <arg name="text" type="string" allow-null="true"/>
    </event>

    <event name="delete_surrounding_text">
      <description summary="delete surrounding text">
       Notify when the text around the current cursor position should be
       deleted. Before_length and after_length is the length (in bytes) of text
       before and after the current cursor position (excluding the selection)
       to delete.

       This event should be handled as part of a following commit_string or
       preedit_string event.
      </description>
      <arg name="before_length" type="uint" summary="length of text before current cursor position"/>
      <arg name="after_length" type="uint" summary="length of text after current cursor position"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_text_input_manager_v3" version="1">
    <description summary="text input manager">
      A factory for text-input objects. This object is a global singleton.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the wp_text_input_manager">
       Destroy the wp_text_input_manager object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_text_input">
      <description summary="create a new text input object">
       Creates a new text-input object for a given seat.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwp_text_input_v3"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
