<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="transient_seat_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 Andri Yngvason

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Protocol for creating temporary seats">
    The transient seat protocol can be used by clients to create independent
    seats that will be removed when the client disconnects. The client also gets
    a handle to the seat which can be used to remove the seat.
  </description>

  <interface name="zext_transient_seat_manager_v1" version="1">
    <request name="create">
      <description summary="Create a transient seat">
        Create a new seat that is removed when the client closes the connection.

        The client may suggest a name for the seat, but the server may choose
        whichever name it sees fit, except the name must not collide with the
        name of another seat.

        It is suggested that the client choose a sufficiently unique name, e.g.
        something containing the pid and an incremental numeric value.
      </description>
      <arg name="suggested_name" type="string"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="new_id" interface="zext_transient_seat_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the manager">
        Destroy the manager
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zext_transient_seat_v1" version="1">
    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="unspec" value="0"
        summary="Operation failed for unspecified reason"/>
      <entry name="name_taken" value="1"
        summary="The suggested name was already taken"/>
      <entry name="invalid_name" value="2"
        summary="The suggested name contains invalid characters"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="failed">
      <description summary="seat creation failed">
        This event indicates that the seat creation failed. No event is
        generated after this and the client should destroy the transient seat
        object.
      </description>
      <arg name="error" type="uint" enum="error"/>
    </event>

    <event name="ready">
      <description summary="seat has been created">
        This event indicates that the seat has been created and tells the client
        which name was chosen for it. It is generated after the seat is created.
        No event is generated after this.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the seat">
        Destroy the seat
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
