<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="wp_xcursor_configuration_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2018 Simon Ser

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="protocol to configure XCursor themes">
    This protocol allows compositors to advertize XCursor configuration to
    clients.

    Once compositor configuration is received, clients are responsible for
    loading the XCursor theme, creating wl_buffers with cursor images and
    setting the cursor. Clients are free to ignore configuration set by this
    protocol and use different settings: this protocol merely exposes hints.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
    backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
    may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
    Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
    the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
    Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
    version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
    interface version number is reset.
  </description>

  <interface name="zwp_xcursor_configuration_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="XCursor configuration manager">
      A global factory interface for wp_xcursor_configuration objects.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the XCursor configuration manager object">
        Destroy the XCursor configuration manager. This doesn't destroy objects
        created with the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <enum name="device_type">
      <description summary="an input device type">
        Describes input devices that have a cursor and are attached to a seat.
      </description>
      <entry name="pointer" value="1" summary="Pointer"/>
      <entry name="tablet_tool" value="2" summary="Tablet tool"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_device_xcursor_configuration">
      <description summary="create a wp_xcursor_configuration object for a device">
        This creates a new wp_xcursor_configuration object for the input device
        attached to the given seat.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zwp_xcursor_configuration_v1"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat"/>
      <arg name="device" type="uint" enum="device_type"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zwp_xcursor_configuration_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="XCursor configuration for a device">
      A Xcursor configuration object describes XCursor settings for a specific
      device.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this object">
        Using this request a client can tell the server that it is not going to
        use this object anymore.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="all information about the configuration has been sent">
        This event is sent after all other properties of a
        wp_xcursor_configuration have been sent.

        This allows changes to the wp_xcursor_configuration properties to be
        seen as atomic, even if they happen via multiple events.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="theme">
      <description summary="theme configuration">
        The theme event describes XCursor theme configuration for this device.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="theme name"/>
      <arg name="size" type="uint" summary="theme size"/>
    </event>

    <event name="default_cursor">
      <description summary="default cursor name">
        The default_cursor event describes the default XCursor cursor name to be
        used for this device.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="default cursor name"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
