<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xdg_toplevel_decoration_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2018 Simon Ser

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zxdg_toplevel_decoration_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="window decoration manager">
      This interface permits choosing between client-side and server-side
      window decorations for a toplevel surface.

      A window decoration is a user interface component used to move, resize and
      change a window's state. It can be managed either by the client (part of
      the surface) or by the server.

      By advertizing this interface the server anounces support for server-side
      window decorations.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is experimental and
      backward incompatible changes may be made. Backward compatible changes
      may be added together with the corresponding interface version bump.
      Backward incompatible changes are done by bumping the version number in
      the protocol and interface names and resetting the interface version.
      Once the protocol is to be declared stable, the 'z' prefix and the
      version number in the protocol and interface names are removed and the
      interface version number is reset.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="unconfigured_buffer" value="1"/>
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="2"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the decoration manager object">
        Destroy the decoration manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_decoration">
      <description summary="create a new decoration object">
        Create a new decoration object associated with the given toplevel.

        Creating a zxdg_toplevel_decoration_v1 from a xdg_toplevel which has a
        buffer attached or committed is a client error, and any attempts by a
        client to attach or manipulate a buffer prior to the first
        zxdg_toplevel_decoration_v1.configure call must also be treated as
        errors.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zxdg_toplevel_decoration_v1"/>
      <arg name="toplevel" type="object" interface="xdg_toplevel"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zxdg_toplevel_decoration_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="decoration object for a toplevel surface">
      The decoration object allows the client to switch between a client-side
      and server-side window decoration for a toplevel surface.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the decoration object">
        Switch back to client-side-only window decoration mode.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_mode">
      <description summary="set the decoration mode">
        Set the toplevel surface decoration mode.

        After requesting a decoration mode, the compositor will respond by
        emitting a xdg_surface.configure event. The client should then update
        its content, drawing it with or without decorations depending on the
        received mode. The client must also acknowledge the configure when
        committing the new content (see xdg_surface.ack_configure).

        The compositor can ignore this request.
      </description>
      <arg name="mode" type="uint" enum="mode" summary="the decoration mode"/>
    </request>

    <event name="preferred_mode">
      <description summary="advertise the server's preferred mode">
        The preferred_mode event describes the server's preferred decoration
        mode for this toplevel surface. The event is sent when binding to the
        decoration object and whenever the preferred mode changes.
      </description>
      <arg name="mode" type="uint" enum="mode" summary="the preferred mode"/>
    </event>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="suggest a surface change">
        The configure event asks the client to change its decoration mode. The
        configured state should not be applied immediately. See
        xdg_surface.configure for details.
      </description>
      <arg name="mode" type="uint" enum="mode" summary="the decoration mode"/>
    </event>

    <enum name="mode">
      <description summary="window decoration modes">
        These values describe window decoration modes.
      </description>
      <entry name="client" value="1" summary="client-side window decoration"/>
      <entry name="server" value="2" summary="server-side window decoration"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
